A Guide to the Blacksburg Vertical Files (List of Subjects), 1960s-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Blacksburg Vertical Files (List of Subjects), 1960s-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
VerticalFile.001
11.21 Cubic Feet 20 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Newman Library staff began collection materials for vertical files during the 1960s. Special Collections staff add to existing files and continue to create new files as the need arises.
Scope and Content
In general, vertical files at Special Collections include newspaper clippings, photocopies, ephemera, unpublished and/or informal publications, and other papers relating to a specific subject area. Files in this collection relate to Blacksburg and its history. Each topic below has at least one folder and many include cross references.
Arrangement
Vertical files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Montgomery County/Christiansburg Vertical Files
Southwest Virginia Vertical Files
Biographical Vertical Files (mostly relating to Virginia Tech and/or local history)
Record Group Vertical Files (history of Virginia Tech colleges, departments, administrative units, and organizations)
Virginia Tech and Local History Mounted Clippings (precursor to the vertical files, with materials dating back to the 1870s)
Index Terms
Genre and Form Terms:
Vertical files
Subjects:
Montgomery County (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Blacksburg (Va.); Women -- History
Contents List
- Airport - VPI / Blacksburg (see also University Archives Record Group 6/3/3)
- Alexander Black House (see Black (Alexander) House)
- American National Red Cross
- Animal Control
- Annexation
- Art
- Arts and Crafts (see Art)
- Athletics (2 folders)
- Awards and Rankings (see also Blacksburg in the Eighties)
- Banks (see also National Bank of Blacksburg)
- Baptist Church, Blacksburg (see also Baptist Church, Blacksburg - black, pre-1959; Churches; Community Federation)
- Baptist Church, Blacksburg - black, pre 1959 (see also Baptist Church, Blacksburg; Churches)
- Bicentennial
- Bike Club, Blacksburg
- Bikeways (see also Huckleberry Trail)
- Black (Alexander) House (see also Buildings and Houses; Museums)
- Black History
- Blacksburg Baptist Church (see Baptist Church, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Baptist Church - black, pre-1959 (see Baptist Church, Blacksburg - black, pre-1959)
- Blacksburg Bike Club (see Bike Club, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Christian Church (see Christian Church, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Comprehensive Plan (see Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Electronic Village
- Blacksburg Federation of Neighborhoods (see Federation of Neighborhoods, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Group
- Blacksburg in the Eighties (BITE) (see also Awards and Rankings)
- Blacksburg Lions Club (see Lions Club, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Methodist Church (see Methodist Church, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Museum of History (see Price House; Black (Alexander) House)
- Blacksburg Music Club (see Music Club, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg Presbyterian Church (see Presbyterian Church, Blacksburg)
- Blacksburg-Roanoke Link - Blacksburg (see Smart Road - Construction)
- Blacksburg-Roanoke Link - Smart Road (see Smart Road - Technology)
- Blacksburg Transit (see Mass Transit)
- Blacksburg United Methodist Church (see United Methodist Church, Blacksburg)
- Block Party Ordinance Controversy
- Boy and Girl Scouts
- Budget and Financing
- Buildings and Houses (4 folders) (see also Business and Industry; Catholic Churches; Downtown Blacksburg; Five Chimneys; Historic Homes; Kent Square; for Pagoda House, see also Currie, Leonard J. biographical file; for Solitude, see University Archives Record Group 6/2/3b)
- Business and Industry (7 folders) (see also Chamber of Commerce; Awards and Rankings; Buildings and Houses)
- Catholic Churches (see also Buildings Houses, Folder 2, 3-Way Property Exchange Between St Mary's, Francis Anglican and Odd Fellows Lodge)
- Cemeteries (see also Cemeteries - Montgomery County)
- Chamber of Commerce (see also Business and Industry; Awards and Rankings; Community Federation)
- Christ Episcopal Church (see also Churches; Community Federation)
- Christian Church, Blacksburg
- Christian Science
- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints
- Churches Baptist churches (see also Baptist Church, Blacksburg; Baptist Church, Blacksburg - black, pre-1959; Catholic Churches; Christ Episcopal Church; Christian Church, Blacksburg; Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints; Good Shepherd Church of the Brethren; Luther Memorial Lutheran Church; Northside Presbyterian Church; Methodist Church, Blacksburg; Presbyterian Church, Blacksburg; Slusser's Chapel Church of God; United Methodist Church, Blacksburg)
- Citizen's Forum
- City Status (3 folders)
- Cloning (see PPL Therapeutics)
- Clubs (2 folders) (see also Community Federation; names of individual clubs)
- Clubs, pre-1959 (see also Community Federation - Blacksburg)
- Community Center
- Community Federation
- Community Organizations and Programs (see also United Way)
- Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg
- Corning Glass Works
- Crime and Law Enforcement (2 folders) (see also Police Department; Fire Department; biographical files under individual names)
- Data Services Corporation
- Deadwood Days (see also Steppin' Out Festival)
- Demonstrations (see Political Activism and Demonstrations)
- Development (see Planning, Zoning and Development)
- Downtown Blacksburg (2 folders) (see also Buildings and Houses; Historic Homes; Kent Square)
- Draper's Meadow (2 folders) (see also History, to 1900; Smithfield; biographical file on Ingles, Mary; biographical file on Patton, James; Preston Family Papers)
- Economy and Economic Development (see also Awards and Rankings, Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg; Business and Industry; Blacksburg-VPI&SU Relations, Record Group 6/5-f)
- Elections (see Voting and Elections)
- Electro Tec (see also Litton Industries' Polyscientific Corp)
- Electronic Village (see Blacksburg Electronic Village)
- Environment
- Farmer's Market
- Federal Mogul Corporation
- Federation of Neighborhoods, Blacksburg
- Festivals (see also Art; Deadwood Days; Steppin' Out Festival)
- Fire Department
- Fires
- First Aid & Life Saving Crew (see Fire Department)
- First and Main Shopping Center
- Five Chimneys
- 460 Corridor (see also Smart Road - Construction; Smart Road - Technology;; Route 460/114 Corridor Development Plans & Standards (HT393 V82 R68 1988); Shopping Centers - Montgomery County; Business and Industry - Montgomery County; Business and Industry - Christiansburg)
- Garden Club
- Girl Scouts (see Boy and Girl Scouts)
- Good Shepherd Church of the Brethren
- Government, 1976- (see also Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg; Economy and Economic Development; Planning, Zoning and Development; Town Council; Voting and Elections)
- Government, Pre-1976
- Haleos Technology, Inc.
- Health and Safety (2 folders)
- Heritage Hall
- Historic Homes (see also Buildings and Houses)
- Historical Museums (see Black (Alexander) House; Museums; Price House)
- History, to 1900 (2 folders) (see also Buildings and Houses - Blacksburg; Business and Industry - Blacksburg; Smithfield; bio file on Ingles, Mary; bio file on Patton, James; Preston Family Papers)
- History, 1901-1950 (see also Buildings and Houses - Blacksburg; Business and Industry - Blacksburg; Civilian Defense Council, WWII; Housing - Blacksburg (Housing Problems for Tech students after WWII); Goodridge Wilson, "Notes on Blacksburg")
- History, 1951-present (see also Blacksburg Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg-Roanoke Link; Buildings and Houses - Blacksburg; Downtown Blacksburg; Business and Industry - Blacksburg; City Status - Blacksburg; Military - Blacksburg)
- Hotels and Motels
- Housing (2 folders) (see also Hotels and Motels; Planning, Zoning and Development; for Greek Housing, see University Archives Record Group 8/2/1)
- Hoy Funeral Home (see Black (Alexander) House)
- Huckleberry Railroad
- Huckleberry Trail (see also Bikeways)
- Kent Square
- Land Swap - '86-'87 (see also 460 Corridor; Shopping Centers - Montgomery County; biographical file on Matthews, William)
- Legal Actions (see also Annexation; Buildings and Houses, folder 2 (Thomas-Conner House); Housing (Cluster Housing); Planning, Zoning and Development, folders 1 and 2; for Greek Housing, see University Archives Record Group 8/2/1)
- Licenses
- Lions Club, Blacksburg
- Liquor By The Drink (see also Blue Laws - Montgomery Co)
- Litton Industries' Poly-Scientific Division (see also Electro Tec)
- Luther Memorial Lutheran Church (see also Churches -Blacksburg)
- Lyric Theatre (see also Buildings and Houses)
- Maps
- Mass Transit System, pre-1983 (see also Transportation)
- Mass Transit System, 1983-1988 (see also Transportation)
- Mass Transit System, 1989- (see also Transportation; Two-Town Trolley)
- Media
- Methodist Church, Blacksburg (see also United Methodist Church, Blacksburg; Churches; Community Federation)
- Military (see also Building and Houses (Armory); History, 1901-1950)
- Municipal Building
- Municipal Complex Design Competition
- Museums (see also Black (Alexander) House; Price House)
- Music Club, Blacksburg
- National Bank of Blacksburg (see also Banks)
- Nellie's Cave
- Newcomers' Club
- Nicewonder
- Northside Presbyterian Church (see also Churches; Presbyterian Church, Blacksburg)
- Oil Well, Price Mountain
- Olin and Preston Institute
- PPL Therapeutics (Cloning)
- Parking
- Parks (see also Recreation)
- Performing Arts (2 folders) (see also Music Club, Blacksburg)
- Planning, Zoning and Development (3 folders) (see also Housing; for Greek Housing, see University Archives Record Group 8/2/l)
- Police Department (see also Crime and Law Enforcement)
- Political Activism and Demonstrations
- Politics (see also Voting and Elections)
- Poly-Scientific (see Litton Industries' Poly-Scientific Division)
- Population (see also Blacksburg in the Eighties (BITE); Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg; Buildings and Houses; Chamber of Commerce; City Status; Economy and Economic Development; 460 Corridor; History - 1951-present; Housing; Mass Transit; Parking; Planning, Zoning and Development; Roads; Smart Road - Construction; Two-Town Trolley)
- Post Office
- Presbyterian Church, Blacksburg
- Price House
- Price's Fork (see Price's Fork - Montgomery County)
- Demonstrations (see Political Activism and Demonstrations)
- Protests (see Political Activism and Demonstrations)
- Public Works (see also Awards and Rankings; Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg; Downtown Blacksburg; Huckleberry Trail; Mass Transit System; Steppin' Out; Utilities)
- Racial and Ethnic Minorities (see also Black History)
- Raft Community Crisis Center
- Recreation, pre-1959
- Recreation (2 folders) (see also Community Center; Parks)
- Red Cross (see American National Red Cross)
- Rescue Squad (see Fire Department)
- Restaurants (3 folders)
- Retirement
- Roads (2 folders) (see also Smart Road - Construction; Smart Road - Technology; 460 Corridor; Downtown Blacksburg; Nellie's Cave Road; Planning, Zoning and Development)
- Rotary Club
- School Controversies (see also Buildings and Houses - Blacksburg (Armory); Schools)
- Schools (6 folders) (see also School Controversies)
- Scouts (see Boy and Girl Scouts)
- Shopping Centers (see also First and Main Shopping Center; Kent Square)
- Signs
- Sister City
- Slusser's Chapel Church of God
- Smart Road - Construction (3 folders) (see also 460 Corridor; Smart Road - Technology)
- Smart Road - Technology (see also 460 Corridor; Smart Road - Construction)
- Smithfield (3 folders)
- Sports (see Athletics)
- Spring Houses
- Steppin' Out Festival (see also Deadwood Days)
- Taxes and Bonds
- Top 10 Stories of Year
- Tour DuPont
- Town Council (see also Blacksburg in the Eighties (BITE); Budget and Financing; City Status; Community Federation; Comprehensive Plan, Blacksburg; Downtown Blacksburg; Economy and Economic Development; Government; Legal Actions; Planning, Zoning and Development; Taxes and Bonds; Telecommunications Towers - Montgomery County)
- Town Personnel (see also Awards and Rankings; Police Department; Fire Department; Mass Transit System)
- Transportation (see also Mass Transit System)
- Two-Town Trolley (see also Mass Transit System)
- United Methodist Church (see Churches; United Methodist Church, Blacksburg)
- United Way
- Utilities (see also Blacksburg-VPI Electric Service (University Archives Record Group 6/3); Blacksburg-VPI Sanitation Authority (University Archives Record Group 6/3/6-a); A New Water System: Blacksburg, Christiansburg, Virginia Polytechnic Institute (TD224 V8 B5 1957 Large Spec); Public Works)
- Virginia College of Osteopathic Medicine
- Voting and Elections
- Warm Hearth, Inc
- Weather
- Weather Station
- Women
- Zoning (see also Planning, Zoning and Development)